Guide to the Washington State Grange Records 1889-1953
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Washington State Grange Records
1889-1953
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 218
Washington State Grange
6 Linear feet of shelf space 10 Boxes
Papers of the Washington State Grange, including: Miscellaneous mimeographed announcements, letters; Grange newspapers and magazines; Grange rosters; annual sessions proceedings; three scrapbooks of news clippings from the Grange News.
In September, 1889, Washington State farmers organized the Washington State Grange. They saw the Grange as a means of fraternal cooperation in the promotion of agricultural interests, and as a method of providing education and recreation for their families. The Grange was also a vehicle for increasing the public's awareness of farmers' issues and for winning legislation to ease farmers' problems associated with the high cost of goods and services, and the low prices received for commodities. The Grange in later years became one of the principal general farmers' organizations, and as such has since functioned as a public and legislative spokeman for agricultural interests. The Grange also takes public positions of advocacy or opposition on a variety of issues such as general economic policy, transportation, and public works projects.
Papers of the Washington State Grange, including: Miscellaneous mimeographed announcements, letters; Grange newspapers and magazines; Grange rosters; annual sessions proceedings; three scrapbooks of news clippings from the Grange News.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Little information is available about the source of most of the materials in this collection. The three scrapbooks were donated to the Washington State University Libraries in 1970 by Henry P. Carsterson, Past Master, Washington State Grange.
Crawford, Harriet Ann. The Washington State Grange, 1889-1924; a Romance of Democracy. Portland, Or.: Binfords & Mort;, 1940.
Washington State Grange Records, 1954-1979 (Cage 512)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State Grange -- Records and correspondence.
Agriculture -- Washington (State) -- Societies, etc. -- Records and correspondence.; Agriculture, Cooperative -- Washington (State) -- Records and correspondence.
Agriculture; Washington (State)
- Miscellaneous mimeographed announcements, letters, etc. (Box 1)
- Grange publications (newspapers and magazines). Includes Modern Farmer, vol. 1, no. 9, 1932 June; Agricultural Grange News (Olympia, WA), vol. V, no. 5, 1917 February 1; Grange Facts (Seattle), no. 1, 1930 September 5; Grange News (Seattle), SSVII, no. 46, 1938 November 19 and XVII, no. 17, 1928 August 5. (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous printed material. Includes Patrons of Husbandry by-laws (1921, 1929, 1931-1933); Program of Washington State Grange annual session (1916, 1918, 1920, 1925, 1934, 1935, 1937, 1939, 1941, 1942). (Box 1)
- Washington State Grange Rosters (1913-1915, 1917-1930, 1933, 1935, 1938-1940, 1945-1946, 1946-1953). (Box 2-3)
- Report of the Secretary (1912, 1915, 1917, 1920, 1925, 1926, 1931-1933, 1935, 1937-1939, 1942). (Box 3)
- Proceedings of the Annual Session of the Washington State Grange (1889, 1892, 1893, 1899-1901, 1903, 1904, 1907-1942, 1948-1950,1958-1960, 1962-1969, 1976) (Box 4-7)
- Washington State Grange Rosters (1937, 1939, 1960, 1963-1970). (Box 7)
- Washington State Grange Handbook (1966, 1968-1970). (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous pamphlets. (Box 7)
- Grange News issues, 1960. (Box 7)
- Book: Grange Melodies (1916). (Box 7)
- Scrapbooks (clippings from the Grange News), 3 volumes (1944 April-1948 February; 1941 June-1944 April; 1948 March-1953 June). (Box 8-10)